Hello everyone, today we are going to talk about a
大家好，今天我們要談論一個
core framework that I think can completely change the way you interact with AI
核心框架，我認為它可以完全改變你與 AI 互動的方式
Hey, this is not the kind of layer-by-layer technique that the king of learning will soon have
嘿，這不是那種分層技術，學習之王很快就會擁有的
but a brand-new mode of thought
而是一種全新的思維模式
so that we can really think with AI
讓我們能夠真正與 AI 一起思考
Okay, let's get started
好的，讓我們開始吧
I believe that many people are like me
我相信許多人像我一樣
living in an era where AI changes every day
生活在一個 AI 每天都在變化的時代
It feels like I've been pushed by the waves of the times
感覺就像被時代的浪潮推著走
Sometimes it's really a bit out of control
有時候真的有點無法控制
Do you also have this feeling?
你也有這種感覺嗎？
The speed of AI development is really too fast
AI 發展的速度真的太快了
It's so fast that we often ask ourselves
快到我們經常問自己
How do we catch up?
我們如何趕上？
To be honest, this sense of frustration is very anxious
說實話，這種挫折感令人非常焦慮
We may have more or less
我們多多少少可能都有
In fact, these feelings are normal
實際上，這些感受都是正常的
You see, the world has changed so fast
你看，世界變化太快了
Many companies or teams have not yet figured out the strategy
許多公司或團隊還沒有想出策略
So we rushed into AI
所以我們衝向了 AI
The result is that we often have to use some systems that we don't understand at all
結果是我們經常不得不使用一些我們根本不理解的系統
That sense of helplessness is really heavy
那種無助感真的很沉重
Then AI can do things that we can understand intuitively
然後 AI 可以做一些我們能直觀理解的事情
The gap seems to be getting bigger
差距似乎越來越大
Not to mention the so-called prompt density on the Internet
更不用說網際網路上的所謂提示詞密度了
I've been learning for a long time and it's over
我學了很久就結束了
So can we think about this from a different angle?
那麼我們能否從不同的角度來考慮這個問題？
If we don't chase those
如果我們不追逐那些
The technology of the sun, the moon and the sun
日新月異的技術
Instead, pull the focus back to ourselves
而是將焦點拉回到我們自己
To think
去思考
As humans
作為人類
How should we interact with AI
我們應該如何與 AI 互動
Will we find a new way out?
我們會找到新的出路嗎？
You see, these are actually two completely different forms
你看，這實際上是兩種完全不同的形式
The old method is to focus on the technology itself
舊方法是關注技術本身
I've been chasing those short-term techniques all day
整天追趕那些短期技巧
What do you take AI as?
你把 AI 當作什麼？
Well, it's probably a better way to do a拼字检查
嗯，它可能只是一個更好的拼字檢查方式
But the new method is about human-machine cooperation
但新方法是關於人機協作
It's about training our core ability to understand deeply
這是關於培養我們深層理解的核心能力
To treat AI as a reliable partner
把 AI 當作一個可靠的夥伴
So this brings out our core concept today
所以這就引出了我們今天的核心概念
AI fluency
AI 流暢度
To put it bluntly
坦白說
This is an ability to make us able to use efficient
這是一種能力，使我們能夠高效地使用
And also to work with AI in a moral and safe way
並且以道德和安全的方式與 AI 合作
It's not just a skill
這不只是一項技能
It's a stronger and more sustainable mode of cooperation
這是一種更強大、更可持續的合作模式
This AI fluency sounds great
這個 AI 流暢度聽起來不錯
How do we do it?
我們如何做到呢？
The key is to master the four core abilities
關鍵是掌握四個核心能力
Which is the 4D framework we're going to talk about
這就是我們要談的 4D framework
Look at this table, so clear
看這個表格，非常清楚
This whole framework is the core ability of the four Ds
整個框架就是四個 D 的核心能力
Which are the initial English words
這些是最初的英文字母
Fluency, description, recognition, and
流暢度、描述、識別，以及
And intimacy
以及親密度
Each ability corresponds to a key question
每個能力都對應一個關鍵問題
That we must ask ourselves when interacting with AI
這是我們在與 AI 互動時必須問自己的問題
Okay, the first D, fluency
好的，第一個 D，流暢度
This is super important
這非常重要
It's actually asking us a question
它實際上是在問我們一個問題
When should I do it myself?
我什麼時候應該自己做？
When should I let AI do it?
我什麼時候應該讓 AI 來做？
This is a judgment
這是一個判斷
For example, make a market report
例如，製作市場報告
Previous data collection and organization
先前的數據收集和整理
Can be completely handed over to AI
可以完全交給 AI
But the final strategic judgment and decision
但最終的戰略判斷和決策
Of course, it still has to be done by you, the human expert
當然，還是得由你這位人類專家來做
Right?
對吧？
Okay, when you decide what task you want to send
好的，當你決定要發送什麼任務時
What's next?
接下來呢？
Of course, you have to tell him clearly
當然，你必須清楚地告訴他
This is our second D, description
這是我們第二個 D，描述
This is a communication art
這是一門溝通的藝術
How can we make our needs
我們如何才能讓我們的需求
Our intentions
我們的意圖
Speak clearly and accurately
表達得清楚準確
Let AI really understand what we want
讓 AI 真正理解我們想要什麼
But no matter how good your instructions are
但無論你的指令有多好
What AI gives you
AI 給你的東西
It may not be able to use it directly, right?
可能無法直接使用，對吧？
So the third D, recognition
所以第三個 D，辨識
Has become very critical
變得非常關鍵
This requires us to not blindly accept the whole board
這要求我們不要盲目地全盤接受
But with a kind of critical eye
而是以一種批判的眼光
To assess and evaluate the output given by AI
去評估和評價 AI 給出的輸出
Which is right
哪些是正確的
Which is done
哪些已經完成
Which needs to be modified
哪些需要修改
This judgment is very important
這種判斷非常重要
Okay, after you've identified, evaluated
好的，當你識別、評估之後
Even modified the output of AI
甚至修改了 AI 的輸出
The last step is also the most important one
最後一步也是最重要的一步
That is, you have to take responsibility for the whole result
那就是，你必須為整個結果負責
This is the last D, affection
這是最後一個 D，責任
This is a sense of responsibility
這是一種責任感
We have to make sure that the whole process of cooperation is transparent
我們必須確保整個合作過程是透明的
Can be traced
可以追蹤
And we are willing to be responsible for the final result
而且我們願意為最終結果負責
So we just talked about
所以我們剛才談到的
Description, description, identification, affection
描述、說明、辨識、責任
You may think
你可能會想
Learn these
學習這些
What's the difference with those who teach you how to do PROMPT
與那些教你怎麼做 PROMPT 的人有什麼區別
Hey, that's a big difference
嘿，差別很大
This framework helps us to build
這個框架幫助我們建立
Is a more objective and longer-term thought
是一種更客觀且長期的思維
Not only to deal with today's AI
不僅要應對今天的 AI
No matter what AI becomes in the future
無論將來 AI 變成什麼樣子
You have a way to deal with it
你都有辦法應對
You see
你看
Once you have mastered this framework of AI fluency
一旦你掌握了 AI 流暢性這個框架
What you get is not just
你得到的不僅僅是
Write better PROMPT
寫得更好的 PROMPT
This kind of skill
這種技能
You will have a guide principle
你會擁有一個指導原則
Use in any interaction with AI
應用在任何與 AI 的互動中
You will be more confident
你會更加自信
Know when to use
知道何時使用
How to use AI
如何使用 AI
More importantly
更重要的是
What you cultivate is a profound
你培養的是一種深刻的
And the ability to take away
以及帶走的能力
At the same time, I also learned to be responsible for the result
同時，我也學會了為結果負責
Actually, I think this sentence is very good
實際上，我認為這句話非常好
It perfectly summarizes everything we talked about today
它完美地總結了我們今天談論的一切
Our goal is to fundamentally change
我們的目標是從根本上改變
The way we interact with AI
我們與 AI 互動的方式
We don't just want to change how we think about AI
我們不只是想改變我們對 AI 的看法
But to learn how to think with AI
而是學習如何與 AI 一起思考
This is a layered leap
這是一個分層的飛躍
So after listening to today's content
所以聽完今天的內容後
I want to leave a question for everyone to go back and think about
我想給大家留下一個問題，回去思考
In your work or study
在你的工作或學習中
How do you plan to use the 4D framework that describes the identification surface
你計畫如何使用描述識別表面的 4D framework
To establish a firm tacit understanding with AI
與 AI 建立堅實的默契
What about stronger partner relationships?
以及建立更強大的夥伴關係？